Guide to the Allen L. McKellar papers, 1942-1975 and undated RL.11800
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allen L. McKellar papers
1942-1975 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McKellar, Allen L.
RL.11800
3.0 Linear Feet
Allen L. McKellar was an African American sales and marketing executive based primarily in the St. Louis, Mo. area and one of the first business professionals to break the color barrier in major American corporations. The Allen L. McKellar papers include clippings, correspondence, financial and sales reports, photographs, sales training and other manuals, newsletters, research reports and other printed materials relating to McKellar's career marketing Pepsi and Falstaff beer products to African American and minority consumers. Celebrity individuals and civic institutions represented in the collection include Barbara McNair, Chicago Urban League, Hank Aaron, James Brown, National Business League and the United States Brewers' Association. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History, and the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History & Culture.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Falstaff Brewing Files; Printed Material.
Biographical / Historical
Allen L. McKellar was an African American sales and marketing executive based primarily in the St. Louis, Mo. area and one of the first business professionals to break the color barrier in major American corporations.
Allen McKellar was born in 1920 in Abbeville, South Carolina. He graduated from South Carolina Colored Agricultural and Mechanical College (now South Carolina State University) in 1940 and was hired by Pepsi-Cola as part of a program to promote Pepsi consumption in the black community. McKellar served in the U.S. Army during World War II and returned to Pepsi around 1947. In 1951 Pepsi reorganized to focus on international marketing and disbanded its domestic special markets program; McKellar subsequently went to work for Falstaff Brewing, where he worked until he retired in 1975. He died in St. Louis, Mo. in 2018.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Allen L. McKellar papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman and Franklin Center collections:
African American History marketing and promotional posters
Asa & Edna Spaulding papers
Douglass Alligood papers
Garrett Orr papers
J. Walter Thompson Company. Compaetitive advertisements
J. Walter Thompson Company. Corporation vertical files
Tom Burrell papers
Collection Overview
The Allen L. McKellar papers include clippings, correspondence, financial and sales reports, photographs, sales training and other manuals, newsletters, research reports and other printed materials relating to McKellar's career marketing Pepsi and Falstaff beer products to African American and minority consumers. Celebrity individuals and civic institutions represented in the collection include Barbara McNair, Chicago Urban League, Hank Aaron, James Brown, National Business League and the United States Brewers' Association.
Marketing -- United States -- History; Sales promotion -- United States -- History; African American business people; African American consumers; Minority consumers -- United States; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Pepsi-Cola Company; Falstaff Brewing Corporation
- General Files, 1942, 1973-1975; 1
  - NAACP annual convention literature, 1973 (Box 1)
  - National Business League--Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - National Business League--Meeting materials, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Pepsi-Cola correspondence, 1942 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence pertains to Pepsi's participation in the Pittsburgh Courier's "Double V" program, a campaign that combined WWII victory over the Axis powers with victory over discrimination for African Americans back home in the United States. Activities planned included pins, car stickers and contests.
- Falstaff Brewing Company Files, 1952-1975 and undated; 2
  - Advertising Specialties Program merchandise catalog, 1960s (Box 1)
  - Advertising Transition Manual, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Ballantine--New York Metropolitan Area Survey, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Barbara McNair, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Beer consumption patterns 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Big 4 Family News, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Black distributors, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Black market, undated (Box 1)
  - Branch training conference, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Calling cards, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Chicago--Black market study (Box 1)
  - Chicago market, 1960-1972 (Box 1)
  - Chicago--WCIU-26, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Corporate Affirmative Action Program, 1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Don't Buy Coors Beer flyer, undated (Box 1)
  - Draft Beer Guide, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Draft Beer Profit Chart, undated (Box 1)
  - Driver salesman uniforms, 1964, 1970; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Employee military service policy, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Employment practices policy, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Employee stock purchase plan, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Equal Employment Opportunity Seminar, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Events--100% Right Club, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Events--100% Wrong Club, 1973-1975; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Events--Miss Black America, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Events--Miss Black America of Florida, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Events--Miss New Orleans-Miss Louisiana Black America, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Events--Miss New Orleans-Miss Louisiana Black America, 1969 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Events--National Tavern Month, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Events--North-South Golf Tournament, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Events--Orange Blossom Classic golf tournament, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Events--Redd Foxx at Falstaff headquarters, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Events--Temptations concert, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Events--Tom Jones Show, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Events--Tom Jones Show, 1970 (Box 4)
  - Falstaff Merchandiser newsletter, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Falstaff Shield newsletter, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Games booklet, undated (Box 1)
  - Guide for Outings, undated (Box 1)
  - James Brown, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - James Brown--Clippings, 1969 (Box 4)
  - James Brown--Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Logos, labels, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Management conference, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Market Facts--Ale questionnaire, undated (Box 4)
  - Marketing Program Meeting Leader's Guide, 1968 (Box 1)
  - News About Tapper, 1965 (Box 1)
  - News About Tapper, 1965 (Box 4)
  - On the Falstaff Route newsletter, 1959-1964 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
  - Policy Manual, 1956-1974; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Print advertisement, "Beautiful People", 1973 (Box 4)
  - Print advertisement, "Men on the Go" featuring Allen McKellar, 1971 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Promotional/merchandising, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Recruiting and Selection Manual for Field Sales Representatives, Field Advertising Representatives, and Branch Salesmen, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Retail sales figures, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Sales Bulletin, Southeastern Division, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Schlitz in the News, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Shreveport Consumer Study, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Speech--The Ethnic Market, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Stockholder Report, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Telephone directory, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Territory Managers Workshop, 1961 (Box 1)
  - The Black Marketer, 1970 (Box 2)
  - The Falstaff Way, 1952-1972; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - The Falstaff Way Marketing Program, 1968 (Box 2)
  - The Pleasure of Your Company awards catalog, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Tips on Selling the Black Market, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Top 20 music list, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Training manual, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Training Services for Falstaff Distributors, 1964 (Box 2)
  - War Book (marketing promotions), undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - WCIU-TV (Chicago)--Food/liquor store route list, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Welcome to Falstaff, 1961 (Box 2)
- Printed Material, 1950-1972 and undated; 3
  - Brewing and Allied Industries--The Brewing World, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Chicago Tribune--Chicago Market/Media: City of the Big Shoulders, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Chicago Urban League--Facts About the Negro in Chicago, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Urban League--Housing and Race in Chicago, 1963 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Urban League--Notes on Problems of Negro Employment, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Urban League--Policies and programs, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Urban League--The Unskilled Negro Worker in the Chicago Labor Market, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Chicago Urban League--West Side Fact Sheet, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Creative Research Associates--Market Information about Chicagoland's 1,300,000 Blacks, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Crusade for Freedom--Focus newsletter, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Daddy O'Daylie Enterprises--America's Neglected Giant: The Negro Consumer!, undated (Box 3)
  - David Sullivan--Why a Handful of Advertisers Dominate Negro Markets, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Grocery Manufacturer--Mass or Class, Couponing Prospers, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Harold Baron--Negro Unemployment: A Case Study, 1963 (Box 3)
  - John O'Neal (Free Southern Theater) clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - National Association of Market Developers (NAMD)--Conference on Marketing and Public Relations in the Negro Market, 1963 (Box 3)
  - National Association of Market Developers (NAMD)--Convention Proceedings, 1968 (Box 3)
    Includes: The Negro Market in Perspective; Selling to Industry and Their Agencies; Selling to Retailers and Other Intermediaries; What Do Youth Want and Expect from Business
  - Reuben H. Donnelley Corp.--Bargain Power! Black Consumer Direct Marketing Program, 1971 (Box 3)
  - United States Brewers Association (USBA)--Beer Party USA, undated (Box 3)
  - United States Brewers Association (USBA)--Package Beer Manual, 1960s (Box 3)
  - United States Department of Commerce--Minority Business Enterprise Outlook newsletter, 1972 (Box 3)
  - W. Leonard Evans--Ghetto Marketing: What Now?, 1968 (Box 3)
  - WGRT--Selling Chicago's Black Community, 1969 (Box 3)
  - WVON--The Voice of the Negro, 1963 (Box 3)
  - WVON--The Voice of the Negro clippings, 1963 (Box 4)